Tahmid Hasan

Website: https://tahmid04.github.io/ [Google Scholar] [GitHub]

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests are in **Natural Language Processing** with a particular focus on **efficient data** and **compute utilization** under resource-scarce scenarios. My works have so far focused on **low-resource languages** and **multilingual/cross-lingual** language models. My goal is to build practical and general-purpose NLP systems that can learn to communicate with speakers of all languages with limited supervision.

EDUCATION

• Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

M.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering; CGPA: 3.90/4.0

Dhaka, Bangladesh April 2019 - Present

• Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering; CGPA: 3.98/4.0

Dhaka, Bangladesh February 2015 - April 2019

Email: tahmidhasan@cse.buet.ac.bd

PUBLICATIONS

XL-Sum: Large-Scale Multilingual Abstractive Summarization for 44 Languages
 Tahmid Hasan, Abhik Bhattacharjee, Md. Saiful Islam, Kazi Mubasshir, Yuan-Fang Li, Yong-Bin Kang, M. Sohel Rahman, Rifat Shahriyar
 In Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics: ACL-IJCNLP 2021. [PDF] [Code]

2. Not Low-Resource Anymore: Aligner Ensembling, Batch Filtering, and New Datasets for Bengali-English Machine Translation

Tahmid Hasan, Abhik Bhattacharjee, Kazi Samin, Masum Hasan, Madhusudan Basak, M. Sohel Rahman, Rifat Shahriyar

In Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, EMNLP 2020. [PDF] [Code]

3. CoDesc: A Large Code-Description Parallel Dataset

Masum Hasan, Tanveer Muttaqueen, Abdullah Al Ishtiaq, Kazi Sajeed Mehrab, Md. Mahim Anjum Haque, **Tahmid Hasan**, Wasi Ahmad, Anindya Iqbal, Rifat Shahriyar In Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics: ACL-IJCNLP 2021. [PDF] [Code]

4. Using Adaptive Heartbeat Rate on Long-Lived TCP Connections

M. Saifur Rahman, Md. Yusuf Sarwar Uddin, **Tahmid Hasan**, M. Sohel Rahman, M. Kaykobad In *IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (Volume: 26, Issue: 1, Feb. 2018)*. [PDF] [Code]

Under Review/Pre-print:

1. BanglaBERT: Combating Embedding Barrier in Multilingual Models for Low-Resource Language Understanding

Abhik Bhattacharjee*, **Tahmid Hasan*** (*Equal contribution*), Kazi Samin, Md Saiful Islam, M. Sohel Rahman, Anindya Iqbal, Rifat Shahriyar *ArXiv Pre-print*, 2021. [PDF] [Code]

2. BERT2Code: Can Pretrained Language Models be Leveraged for Code Search?
Abdullah Al Ishtiaq, Masum Hasan, Md. Mahim Anjum Haque, Kazi Sajeed Mehrab, Tanveer Muttaqueen, Tahmid Hasan, Anindya Iqbal, Rifat Shahriyar

ArXiv Pre-print, 2021. [PDF]

1. Adapting XL-Sum for Many-to-Many Cross-Lingual Summarization: The target language of a multilingual model on cross-lingual summarization is limited to only the language it is fine-tuned on, and we have observed that fine-tuning with multiple languages without cross-lingual supervision cannot help control the language of the generated summaries. In this work, we generate summaries in any target language for a given article by fine-tuning multilingual models with explicit (albeit limited) cross-lingual signals. We align identical articles across languages via cross-lingual retrieval on the XL-Sum dataset and curate a large-scale cross-lingual summarization dataset containing 1.65 million article-summary samples in over 1500 language pairs. To effectively train cross-lingual summarization models, we introduce a multistage data sampling algorithm and propose a metric for automatically evaluating summaries when references in the target language are unavailable.

Supervisors: Prof. Rifat Shahriyar, Dr. Yuan-Fang Li and Dr. Wasi Uddin Ahmad Status: Ongoing

2. Multilingual Paraphrase Generation via Knowledge Distillation from NMT Models: Instead of doing round-trip translation to generate synthetic paraphrase pairs, in this work, we directly distill the paraphrasing knowledge of multilingual machine translation models into a paraphrase generation model. Using a forward and a backward NMT model as teachers, we distill the cross-attention and output distributions into a student paraphrasing model. In contrast to traditional KD, here we have two teachers instead of one, and the student model's task is different from the teachers'.

Supervisors: Prof. Rifat Shahriyar and Dr. Wasi Uddin Ahmad Status: Ongoing

3. XL-Sum: Large-Scale Multilingual Abstractive Summarization for 44 Languages: We present XL-Sum, a comprehensive and diverse dataset comprising 1 million professionally annotated article-summary pairs in 44 languages from BBC News, extracted using a set of carefully designed heuristics. We perform extensive evaluation to demonstrate the high-quality, conciseness and abstractiveness of XL-Sum. We show higher than 11 ROUGE-2 scores on ten languages tested, with some of them exceeding 15, as obtained by multilingual training. We release the dataset, evaluation scripts, and models for future research on multilingual summarization.

Supervisors: Prof. Rifat Shahriyar and Dr. Yuan-Fang Li Status: Published in Findings of ACL, 2021.

4. BanglaBERT: Limitations of Embedding Barrier for Low-Resource Language Understanding: In this work, we build BanglaBERT – a BERT-based Bangla NLU model pre-trained on 18.6 GB data we meticulously crawled from top Bangla sites. We establish the 'Bangla Language Understanding Evaluation' (BLUE) benchmark and achieve strong baselines on all BLUE tasks with BanglaBERT. Through comprehensive experiments, we identify a significant shortcoming of multilingual models, which we name the 'Embedding Barrier,' that hurts performance for low-resource languages that do not share writing scripts with any high-resource language.

Supervisors: Prof. Rifat Shahriyar and Dr. Wasi Uddin Ahmad Status: Submitted to ARR 2021

5. Not Low-Resource Anymore: Aligner Ensembling, Batch Filtering, and New Datasets for Bengali-English Machine Translation: In this work, we identify that erroneous sentence segmentation and presence of noise deteriorates the quality of sentence alignments for Bengali. Therefore, we build a customized sentence segmenter for Bengali and introduce two methods for sentence alignment from noisy comparable document corpora on low-resource setups: aligner ensembling and batch filtering. Our proposed methods improve alignment F-1 score by 3.38% and translation BLEU score by 2.5 points. We release the data and code for future research on low-resource machine translation.

Supervisors: Prof. Rifat Shahriyar and Prof. M. Sohel Rahman Status: Published in EMNLP, 2020.

6. CoDesc: A Large Code—Description Parallel Dataset: In this study, we present CoDesc – a large parallel dataset composed of 4.2 million Java methods and natural language descriptions. With extensive analysis, we identify and remove prevailing noise patterns from the dataset. We demonstrate the proficiency of CoDesc in two complementary tasks for code-description pairs: code summarization

and code search.

Supervisors: Prof. Rifat Shahriyar and Dr. Wasi Uddin Ahmad Status: Published in Findings of ACL, 2021.

7. BERT2Code: Can Pretrained Language Models be Leveraged for Code Search?: We leverage the efficacy of pretrained word and code embeddings using a simple, lightweight neural network for semantic code search. We show that our model learns the inherent relationship between the embedding spaces, and we further probe into the scope of improvement by empirically analyzing the embeddings. We show that the quality of the code embeddings is the bottleneck for our model's performance and discuss future directions in this area.

Supervisor: Prof. Rifat Shahriyar Status: Completed

8. **Phylogenetic Tree Estimation from Quartets**: In this work, we propose a hybrid algorithm for accurate phylogenetic tree reconstruction from quartets combining distance- and frequency-based approaches. We prove the proposed algorithm to be statistically consistent and achieve good experimental results on simulated datasets.

Supervisors: Prof. M. Sohel Rahman and Prof. Shamsuzzoha Bayzid Status: Completed

9. Using Adaptive Heartbeat Rate on Long-Lived TCP Connections: We propose a set of iterative probing techniques, namely binary, exponential, and composite search, that detect the middle-box binding timeout of long-lived TCP connections and in the process, improve keep-alive intervals of mobile devices. Our proposed methods outperform the native Android keep-alive algorithm and improve notification delivery success by 11%.

Supervisors: Prof. M. Saifur Rahman and Prof. M. Sohel Rahman Status: Published in IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (Vol. 26-1, 2018).

Professional Experience

• Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Lecturer, Department of CSE, BUET

Dhaka, Bangladesh October 2019 - Present

• Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)
Graduate Research Assistant, Department of CSE, BUET
Supervisor: Prof. Rifat Shahriyar

Dhaka, Bangladesh April 2019 - Present

TEACHING EXPERIENCE (SELECTED)

- CSE 472 Machine Learning Sessional: Jan'20, Jul'21
- CSE 204 Data Structures & Algorithms I Sessional: Jul'19, Jul'21
- CSE 412 Simulation & Modeling Sessional: Jan'20
- CSE 308 Software Engineering Sessional: Jan'21
- CSE 216 Database Sessional: Jul'21

- CSE 218 Numerical Methods: Jul'19, Jul'21
- CSE 204 Data Structures & Algorithms II Sessional: Jan'20
- CSE 462 Algorithm Engineering Sessional: Jan'20
- CSE 408 Software Development: Jul'19
- CSE 108: Object Oriented Programming Language Sessional: Jan'21

Honors & Awards

- University Merit Scholarships in each semester for excellent postgraduate results: 2019 2021
- Dean's Award in each academic year for excellent undergraduate results: 2015 2019
- University Merit Scholarships in each semester for excellent undergraduate results: 2015 2019
- Bronze Medal, Asian Pacific Mathematics Olympiad: 2013
- National Champion, Bangladesh Mathematical Olympiad: 2010, 2011, 2013, 2014
- National Champion, Bangladesh Olympiad in Informatics: 2012, 2013

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, C/C++, Java
- Frameworks: PyTorch, Keras, TensorFlow

SELECTED COURSES

• Artificial Intelligence

- Machine Learning
- Pattern Recognition

- Advanced Artificial Intelligence
- Data Mining

• Distributed Computing Systems

SERVICES

• Coach

BUET International Collegiate Programming Contest Teams (2020, 2021)

• Member

BUET CSE Academic Curriculum Modification Committee (2020 - 2021)

REFERENCE

Rifat Shahriyar Professor

Department of CSE, BUET

Email: rifat@cse.buet.ac.bd

Yuan-Fang Li Senior Lecturer

Deapr
tment of Data Science & AI, $\,$

Monash University

Email: yuanfang.li@monash.edu

Wasi Uddin Ahmad Applied Scientist

AWS AI

Email: wuahmad@amazon.com